A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, S-Z FA394
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Sawyer, Wilbur A.
  - 1940 December 14- 1941 March 10, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 94 pages (Reel M Saw 2, Frame 724, Box 426)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. He visits Europe to determine effects of World War II on Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division programs and how long the IHD can remain active during the war. The dairy documents Sawyer's tours and surveys laboratories, public health programs and medical facilities.
    Diaries; Nursing; Influenza; Hygiene; France; Europe; England; Yellow fever -- Vaccination; Typhus fever; Tropical medicine; Spain; Public health; Portugal; Nutrition
  - 1941 1 January- 29 June- Andrew J. Warren Acting- Diary, 1941 January 1- June 29; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Warren, Andrew J.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division
    Organized according to interview and visit, Andrew J. Warren acting on behalf of Wilbur Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. Warren is filling in for Sawyer at the New York office while Sawyer is assessing Rockefeller Foundation International Health Division interests in Europe.
    United States; Vaccines; Nutrition; Public health; Malaria; Nursing; Diaries; Influenza; Yellow fever
  - 1941 June 30-August 5, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation; 17 pages (Box 426, Reel M Saw 2, Frame 948)
    Diaries
  - 8 July- 31 December Diary-Andrew J. Warren Acting, 1941 July 8- December 31; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Warren, Andrew J.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; 198 pages
    Organized according to interview and visit, Andrew J. Warren acting on behalf of Wilbur Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. He attends various conferences on epidemic diseases.
    Yellow fever; Vaccines; United States; Typhus fever; Sanitation; Nutrition; Public health; Influenza; Diaries; Malaria; Hygiene
  - Index, 1942; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (Reel M Saw 3, Frame 1, Box 427)
    1942 Index; 13 pages; alphabetical
    United States; Public health
  - 1942 January 2-March 20, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (Reel M Saw 3, Frame 14, Box 427)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. The focus of the International Health Divison's health phase of the war effort includes perfecting the yellow fever vaccine, nutrition, influenza vaccine, studies in typhus and syphilis which all fall under the Divison's larger mission of disease prevention, health services and support for public health education.
    Dysentery; Yellow fever; Vaccines; United States; Typhus fever; Syphilis; Public health; Malaria; Louse; Influenza
  - 1942 March 20-May 29, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (Reel M Saw 3, Frame 108, Box 427)
    One page
    Public health; United States
  - 20 March-22 April Trip to California Index, 1942 20 March-22; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus)
    Public health; United States; Yellow fever; Jaundice
  - 20 March-22 April- Trip to California, 1942 20 March-22 April; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division
    California; Jaundice; Public health; United States; Yellow fever
  - 1942 23 March-22 April- George K. Strode Acting Diary, 1942 23 March-29 May; Strode, George K.; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division
    Organized according to interview and visit, George K. Strode acting on behalf of Wilbur Sawyer at the New York Office talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses the yellow fever vaccination investigation.
    Jaundice; Public health; United States; Yellow fever
  - 1942 June 1-June 30, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (Box 427, Reel M Saw 3, Frame 254)
    A brief dairy arranged according to interview and visit. Discussions with professionals in the field of public health take place as well as attendance to the Conference on jaundice and Encephalitis after Yellow Fever Vaccination.
    Tropical medicine; Public health; Yellow fever; United States; Encephalitis; Dysentery; Malaria; Jaundice
  - 1942 1 July-1 September George K. Strode Acting Diary, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Strode, George K.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division
    Organized according to interview and visit, George K. Strode acting on behalf of Wilbur Sawyer at the New York Office talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals.
    Yellow fever -- Vaccination; Tropical medicine; United States; Nursing; Medical education; Public health; Nutrition; Jaundice; Cholera; Malaria; Louse
  - 1942 September 1-December 31, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division (Reel M Saw 3, Frame 365, Box 427)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. The International Health Divison's mission is disease prevention, health services and support for public health education.
    Dysentery; Medical education; Nursing; Louse; Malaria; Tropical medicine; Typhus fever; Nutrition; Pneumonia; United States; Yellow fever -- Vaccination
  - Index, 1943; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division (Reel M Saw 3, Frame 484, Box 427)
    1943 Index; 11 pages; alphabetical
    Public health; Nutrition; Nursing; Malaria; Yellow fever; United States; Tropical medicine; Influenza; Jaundice
  - 1943 January 4-March 15, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division (Box 427, Reel M Saw 3, Frame 495)
    Influenza; Nutrition; Nursing; Malaria; Jaundice; Yellow fever; United States; Tropical medicine; Public health
  - 1943 10 March 1943- 21 May: George K Strode Acting, 1943 10 March- 21 May; Strode, George K.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus)
    Insect baits and repellents; Jaundice; Louse; Malaria; Nursing; Tropical medicine; Typhus fever; United States; Yellow fever
  - Trip to South America Index, 16 March- 21 May 1943; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division
    1943 Index; 14 pages; arranged by visit and interview
    Ecuador; Hygiene; Insect baits and repellents; Peru; Public health; South America; Yellow fever
  - Trip to South America, 16 March- 21 May 1943; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health during his trip to South America. He surveys the regional public health infrastructure and yellow fever programs.
    Hygiene; Ecuador; Peru; Insect baits and repellents; South America; Public health; Yellow fever
  - 1943 May 21-December 31, Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division (Reel M Saw 3, Frame 676, Box 427)
    Jaundice; Medical education; Malaria; Public health; Nutrition; Typhus fever; Tropical medicine; Yellow fever; United States
  - Index, 1944; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (Reel M Saw 3, Frame 874, Box 427)
    1944 Index; 7 pages; alphabetical
    Typhus fever; Tropical medicine; Vaccines; United States; Medicine, Preventive; Cholera; Public health; Nutrition
  - 1944 January 3-February 3, Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus) (Reel M Saw 3, Frame 881, Box 427)
  - Trip to Mexico and Western United States Index, 1944 3-27 February; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus)
    1944 Index; 6 pages; arranged by visit and interview
    Rabies; Tropical medicine; United States; Medicine, Preventive; Mexico; Nutrition; Public health; Hookworm disease; Influenza; Malaria; Medical education
  - Trip to Mexico and Western United States, 1944 3-31 May; Sawyer, Wilbur A. (Wilbur Augustus); Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division
    Organized according to interview and visit, Sawyer talks to various professionals in the field of public health and discusses projects and proposals. The International Health Divison's mission is disease prevention, health services and support for public health education. Sawyer takes a trip to Mexico to visit their public health programs and the Louse control program. Also includes diary entries following the Mexico trip.
    Influenza; Malaria; Medical education; Medicine, Preventive; Hookworm disease; United States; Tropical medicine; Rabies; Public health; Nutrition; Mexico
- Scannell, Edward J.
  - 1931 (Box 428)
- Schneider, Alan Leo
  - 1964-1967 (Box 428)
- Schwentker, Francis F.
  - 1941-1942 (Box 428)
- Scott, Virgil C.
  - 1957 (Box 428)
  - 1958 January-June (Box 428)
  - 1958 August-December (Box 428)
  - 1959 January-July (Box 429)
  - 1959 August-December (Box 429)
  - 1960 January-May (Box 429)
  - 1960 June-December (Box 429)
  - 1961 January-March (Box 430)
  - 1961 April-August (Box 430)
  - 1961 September-December (Box 430)
  - 1962 January-May (Box 430)
  - 1962 June-December (Box 430)
  - 1963 January-June (Box 430)
  - 1963 July-December (Box 430)
  - 1964 January-July (Box 431)
  - 1964 August-December (Box 431)
  - 1965 January-June (Box 431)
  - 1965 July-December (Box 431)
  - 1966 January-May (Box 431)
  - 1966 June-December (Box 431)
  - 1967 January-June (Box 432)
  - 1967 July-December (Box 432)
  - 1968 (Box 432)
  - 1969 (Box 433)
  - 1970 (Box 433)
  - 1971 (Box 434)
  - 1972 (Box 434)
  - 1973 (Box 435)
  - 1974-1975 (Box 435)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 436)
- Shannon, Raymond C.
  Greece; South America
  - 1931, 1937-1941, 1943 (Box 436)
- Smith, Donald L.
  - 1954-1957 (Box 436)
- Smith, Hugh H.
  Central America; South America
  - 1944-1945 (Box 437)
  - 1946 (Box 437)
  - 1947 (Box 437)
  - 1948-1949 (Box 438)
  - 1950-1952 (Box 438)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 438)
- Smith, Lucian C.
  - 1928-1929 (Box 439)
- Smithburn, Kenneth C.
  Africa
  - 1939-1940, 1942-1944 (Box 439)
  - 1945-1947 (Box 439)
  - 1948, 1953-1954 (Box 440)
  - 1955-1956 (Box 440)
  - 1957-1958 (Box 440)
- Soper, Fred L.
  Egypt; Algeria; South America
  - 1942-1943 (Box 441)
  - 1944-1946 (Box 441)
- Spence, Leslie P.
  - 1954-1955 (Box 441)
- Spoehr, Herman A.
  - 1930-1931 (Box 441)
- Sprague, Ernest W.
  - 1968 (Box 442)
- Sprague, Lucien M.
  - 1967-1969 (Box 442)
- Stamm, Esther S.
  - 1969-1978 (Box 442)
- Stephenson, Marvin E.
  - 1972-1973 (Box 442)
  - 1974 (Box 443)
- Stevens, David H.
  Biographical/Historical note
  David H. Stevens was an influential staff member of the General Education Board (GEB) and Rockefeller Foundation's (RF) Division of the Humanities.
  Born in Wisconsin in 1884, Stevens earned a B.A. (1906) and an M.A. (1910) from Lawrence University. He taught briefly at Northwestern University before moving on to earn an M.A. from Harvard University in 1912 and a Ph.D. in English from the University of Chicago in 1914.
  Following the completion of his doctorate, Stevens remained at the University of Chicago, rising through the ranks of the English department to become a full professor in 1925. He was also active in University administration, holding positions as Dean of the College of Arts, Literature and Science from 1920 to 1922 and Associate Dean of Faculties in 1929. His academic career was briefly interrupted in 1918 when he served in the Intelligence Division of the U.S. Army during World War I.
  In 1930 Stevens left the University of Chicago to join the GEB as vice president, a post he held until 1938. He helped to expand the work of the GEB into the northern states during the Great Depression. In 1932 Stevens took on perhaps his most important position when he was named Director of the Humanities Division of the RF. As the first full-time director, Stevens had a huge impact in shaping the direction of the humanities program of the RF. His seventeen-year tenure saw the foundation undertaking new initiatives in the fields of drama, radio, film, linguistics, literature and history. Stevens and his associate, John Marshall, moved the RF away from its funding of classical studies and archaeology, refocusing the Foundation's efforts on creative fields and international cultural exchanges.
  Following his retirement in 1949, Stevens returned to scholarly pursuits as a research associate at the Huntington Library in San Marino, California. Stevens died in California in 1980 at the age of 95. His passion for the humanities was evident through a life's work that helped to shape the field and the broader cultural life of the United States.
  David H. Stevens recounted his career in Robert E. Gard's A Time of Humanities; An Oral History: Recollections of David H. Stevens as Director in The Division of the Humanities, Rockefeller Foundation, 1930-50.
  - Index, 1932-1942; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Stevens, David Harrison (Box 444, Reel M Ste 1, Frame 1)
    Index 1932-1942, 17 pages arranged by interview
    United States; Norway; Humanities; France; England; Belgium
  - 1932-1934, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Stevens, David Harrison (Reel M Ste 1, Frame 18, Box 444)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Stevens discusses projects and proposals with various professionals in the humanities. The Rockefeller Foundation's Humanities mission is to support general research, advance the training of personnel and promote projects of international significance. He travels Europe assessing grant and project proposals.
    Anthropology; Belgium; Archaeology; England; Catalogs; Humanities; France; Linguistics; Libraries; Music; Norway; Theater; United States; Universities and colleges
  - 1935, Stevens, David Harrison; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities. (Box 444, Reel M Ste 1, Frame 174)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Stevens discusses projects and proposals with various professionals in the humanities. The focus of the Rockefeller Foundation's work in the humanities has changed from research interests of scholars to a greater concentration of cultural diffusion aimed at the general public with grants for museums, drama, film and radio. Internationally, areas of program concentration included cultural interchange through libraries, development of understanding with the Far East, and the improvement of international communication.
    Humanities; Libraries; England; History; Archaeology; Arts; Museums; Linguistics; Theater; Radio; United States
  - 1936, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Stevens, David Harrison (Box 444, Reel M Ste 1, Frame 293)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Stevens discusses projects and proposals with various professionals in the humanities. The Humanities program is to affect contemporary culture and the general public appreciation of drama, film and radio. Internationally, the Humanities would exchange print materials and develop Far East studies programs.
    Libraries; Humanities; United States; Motion pictures; Archaeology; Bibliography; Asian languages
  - 1937, Stevens, David Harrison; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities. (Box 444, Reel M Ste 1, Frame 382)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Stevens discusses projects and proposals with various professionals in the humanities. The Humanities program is to affect contemporary culture and the general public appreciation of drama, film and radio. Internationally, the Humanities would exchange print materials and develop Far East studies programs. The program's work with libraries is chiefly of an international character and is concerned with projects aiming to promote the exchange of bibliographical and source materials.
    Bibliography; United States; Microfilms; Linguistics; Libraries; Humanities; Greece; Encyclopedias and dictionaries; Drama; Cataloging; Radio; Theater; Museums; Nova Scotia
  - 1938 January-June, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Stevens, David Harrison (Reel M Ste 1, Frame 551, Box 444)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Stevens discusses projects and proposals with various professionals in the humanities. The Humanities program's mission is to promote the democratization of culture through grants to universities, museums and libraries; improvements of international communication; and freer use technical devices that invention has given us for disseminating knowledge.
    Broadcasting; Copyright; Drama; Encyclopedias and dictionaries; Humanities; Libraries; Radio; Museums; Motion pictures; Microfilms; United States; Theater
  - 1938 July-December, Stevens, David Harrison; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities. (Box 444, Reel M Ste 1, Frame 674)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Stevens discusses projects and proposals with various professionals in the humanities. The Humanities program's mission is to promote the democratization of culture through grants to universities, museums and libraries; improvements of international communication; and freer use technical devices that invention has given us for disseminating knowledge. Stevens tours various universities to survey the progress of RF Humanities grants.
    Museums; Motion pictures; Humanities; Encyclopedias and dictionaries; United States; Radio; Drama; Canada
  - 1939 January-May, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Stevens, David Harrison (Box 444, Reel M Ste 1, Frame 800)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Stevens discusses projects and proposals with various professionals in the humanities. The goal of the program is a wider diffusion of knowledge and a freer expression of individual abilities in areas such as drama, libraries, museums, radio, film, Latin America and the Far East.
    Arts; Copyright; Bibliography; Microfilms; Libraries; Museums; Motion pictures; Encyclopedias and dictionaries; East Asia; Latin America; Humanities; Theater; United States
  - 1939 June 1- 1940 January 3 (Box 444, Reel M Ste 1, Frame 983)
  - 1940 January 2-June 29, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Stevens, David Harrison (Reel M Ste 2, Frame 1, Box 445)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Stevens discusses projects and proposals with various professionals in the humanities. Grants are made to interests in drama, libraries, Far East studies, Latin America, Radio, and film.
    United States; Microfilms; Mexico; Theater; Music; East Asia; Drama; Cataloging; Bibliography; Libraries; Latin America; Humanities; Encyclopedias and dictionaries
  - 1940 July-December, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Stevens, David Harrison (Box 445, Reel M Ste 2, Frame 174)
    United States; Music; Latin America; Libraries; Mexico; Museums; Drama; East Asia; Education; Humanities
  - 1941, Stevens, David Harrison; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities. (Reel M Ste 2, Frame 325, Box 445)
    The grants of the humanities programs in 1941 focused on protecting human history, and to supply men and materials in time of war. The main areas of interest that were funded included drama, film, radio, libraries, museums, language, Latin America and Far East studies, and American studies.
    Latin America; Libraries; Humanities; Language and languages; Linguistics; Music; Bibliography; Brazil; Theater; Argentina; Education; Encyclopedias and dictionaries; Drama; East Asia; United States; World War II
  - 1942, Stevens, David Harrison; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities. (Reel M Ste 2, Frame 546, Box 445)
    The grants, visits and interviews with professionals in the 1942 diary focus on language study and culture for the war effort, American studies, drama, radio, film, and libraries.
    Linguistics; Libraries; Motion pictures; Microfilms; United States; Theater; Bibliography; World War II; East Asia; Catalogs; Encyclopedias and dictionaries; Education; Latin America; Language and languages
  - Index, 1943; Stevens, David Harrison; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities. (Reel M Ste 2, Frame 746, Box 445)
    1943 Index; 4 pages arranged by interview.
    United States; Linguistics; Libraries; Latin America; Language and languages; Humanities; Encyclopedias and dictionaries; East Asia
  - 1943, Stevens, David Harrison; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities. (Box 445, Reel M Ste 2, Frame 750)
    The grants, visits and interviews with professionals in the field of humanities focus on the war effort, Latin American and Far East studies, and contemporary life and culture. Included in the diary is a pamphlet titled, "The United Nations Series."
  - 1944, Stevens, David Harrison; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities. (Reel M Ste 2, Frame 958, Box 445)
    The grants, visits and interviews with professionals in the field of humanities focus on the war effort, Latin American and Far East studies, and contemporary life and culture.
    Anthropology; Bibliography; East Asia; Education; Encyclopedias and dictionaries; Humanities; Language and languages; Libraries; Linguistics; United States
  - 1945, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Stevens, David Harrison (Reel M Ste 3, Frame 1, Box 446)
    The grants, visits and interviews with professionals in the field of humanities focus on the war effort, Latin American and Far East studies, and contemporary life and culture. Stevens takes a trip to Mexico to survey the Rockefeller Foundation Humanities program in Mexico. The diary includes a list of post war fellowships as well.
    Linguistics; Libraries; Philosophy and religion; Mexico; United States; Drama; Economics; Encyclopedias and dictionaries; Humanities; Language and languages; Latin America
  - 1946, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Stevens, David Harrison (Box 446, Reel M Ste 3, Frame 227)
    The grants, visits and interviews with professionals in the field of humanities focus on language and foreign culture, American studies, and libraries and museums. Stevens tours British universities to determine prospects in Slavic, Near Eastern and Far Near Eastern studies, and effects of World War II on the Press. The diary includes "Mr. David H. Stevens' Calendar of British Visits September 27th- October 26, 1946."
    Cataloging; England; East Asia; Language and languages; Humanities; United States; Linguistics; World War II
  - 1947, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Stevens, David Harrison (Box 446, Reel M Ste 3, Frame 434)
    The grants, visits and interviews with professionals in the field of humanities focus on research and education in languages and foreign cultures, North American studies and on the betterment of libraries, museums, drama, film and radio.
    Libraries; United States; Encyclopedias and dictionaries; Humanities; Drama; Education; East Asia
  - 1948 January-June, Stevens, David Harrison; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities. (Box 446, Reel M Ste 3, Frame 638)